You are listening to Lutheran.radio in Finnish.
Lutheran Mass for Christmas Morning
— A composition by Michael Praetorius.
It is a fine part of the Lutheran Church's musical heritage.
It was composed in the early 17th century,
and the recordings made of it
are often such that they could have been played 400 years ago in some German church.
Complex polyphony,
expressive harmony,
A unique blend of the Renaissance and Baroque.
And yet, it is a very airy and easily listenable piece.
You can listen to it with one ear on the side,
or you can focus completely, and there is much to listen to.
When the Renaissance and Baroque merge,
there are brass instruments,
strings, and organs.
— A festive and even majestic soundscape.
— And then very beautiful,
giving space in every direction
and it's easy to pick out individual elements,
melodies, and harmonies.
It's complemented by a choir that is nuanced and full, polyphonic.
It captures something from the spiritual atmosphere of its time.
There's joy and reverence. There's a reverent anticipation.
It starts very quietly, a bit like the anticipation of Advent,
and then it transforms increasingly into joy and gratitude.
And it's easy to find a familiar hymn among them: "From Heaven Above to Earth I Come."
There are other Christmas hymns as well, but that one is especially easy to recognize, time after time.
And of course, that hymn was composed almost 100 years earlier,
in 1535, when Luther wrote it.
And where did Luther get the idea?
It, of course, comes from the Gospel of Luke, chapter 2,
verses 10, 11, and 12 specifically.
Which go like this:
And the angel said unto them, Be not afraid; for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy which shall be to all the people:
for there is born to you this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord.
And this is the sign unto you; Ye shall find a babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, and lying in a manger.
Scripture taken from The Holy Bible (1885), English Revised Version.